Inventory of the Hede Massing papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Hede Massing papers
1918-1980
83038
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, police reports, clippings, and photographs, relating to Soviet espionage activities in the United States.
Massing, Hede.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Massing was born in 1900 in Austria. She joined the Communist Party around 1920 when she met Gerhart Eisler, her first husband, and prominent member of the German Communist Party.
Between 1933-1937, Massing served as a Soviet espionage agent in the United States. Later she renounced her allegiance to the Soviet Union, after becoming, as she described it, disenchanted with the direction of the Communist movement under Stalin. Following this decision, she became an outspoken anti-Communist.
In 1949, Massing testified in the Alger Hiss espionage trial, where she maintained that Hiss had been involved in Soviet espionage activities.
In 1951, Massing published an account of her work as a Soviet espionage agent in her book, “This Deception.” Massing continued to write and speak publicly about her role in Soviet espionage as well as other subjects for the rest of her life.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, police reports, clippings, and photographs, relating to Soviet espionage activities in the United States.
Copies of French and Swiss police reports, detailing the investigation of the Ignace Reiss murder in 1937.
Chambers, Whittaker.; Hiss, Alger.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Weyl, Nathaniel, 1910-2005; Espionage, Russian--United States.
- Photographs, 1940-1979, undated
  - Press photographs, Paul Massing, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Hede Massing, Paul Massing, friends, 1940-1979 (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Writing
  - "Christmas in Santa Monica," draft, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - "Doomsday for Alger Hiss"
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 4, Box-folder 1: 18)
  - "Im Handgepäck um die Welt", undated
    - Manuscript, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Manuscript, English translation, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "This Deception" correspondence, 1951-1975 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "Why I Don't Ski," draft, 1956-1978 (Box-folder 1: 18)
- Correspondence
  - Roger Baldwin, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Whittaker Chambers, 1951-1959 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Fischer Family, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Babette Hess, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Jeno Kolb, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Paul Massing, 1930-1977 (Box-folder 1: 8, Box-folder 1: 13, Box-folder 1: 15, Box-folder 1: 17, Box-folder 2: 7, Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Albert Ponsold, 1965-1976, undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Upton Sinclair, 1931 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Speaking engagements, 1951-1954 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Real estate, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Financial, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - General correspondence, 1920-1978 (Box-folder 1: 16, Box-folder 2: 4, Box-folder 2: 9, Box-folder 2: 12, Box-folder 2: 16, Box-folder 2: 18)
- Personal, 1926, undated
  - Biographical sketch of Hede Massing, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Resume, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Vienna residency certificate, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 15)
- Ignace Reiss death investigation, French and Swiss police reports, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Gerhart Eisler obituaries, newspaper clippings, 1952-1968 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Ericha Glaser Wallach memorandum, 1957 (Box-folder 2: 14)